A Guide to the Radka Pavlova Architectural Drawings, 1964-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Radka Pavlova Architectural Drawings, 1964-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2000-003
6.67 cu. ft.; 3 folders, 4 oversize folders
Pavlova, Radka
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Radka Pavlova Architectural Drawings were donated to Special Collections in 2000.
Biographical Note
Radka Pavlova was born February 19, 1933 in the town of Oriakhovo, Vratza Region.Her father, Dimitur Pavlov, was a mechanic and her mother, Dimitra Koeva Pavlova, was a housewife. Dimitra was an expert in traditional crafts (handmade wall hangings, embroidery, and crochet).Pavlova had two sisters, one a mathematics teacher, and the other a literature teacher.After graduating high school in Oriakhovo, Radka enrolled at Sofia Polytechnic, graduating in 1956.For two years, she worked as a regional architect in Blagoevgrad and then transferred to Sofia to work in Glavproekt (1958-1973).She the worked in Tunisia for several years and upon her return joined Sofproekt (1981-1988).
Radka Pavlova married Georgi Stanchev, MD in 1958 and had two children. Pavlova's daughter graduated in architecture in 1984 from Sofia Polytechnic. The daughter specialized in historic preservation and worked in Paris, France.The son graduated in medicine in 1966 from Sofia Medical University and also lived in Paris.
Radka Pavlova designed interiors and furniture, as well as urban and landscapes.She won numerous design competitions for cultural centers, parks, and hotels and for European monuments to important individuals and events.
Scope and Content
The Radka Pavlova Architectural Drawings consists of a portfolio, original drawings, resume, clippings and photocopies.The material reflects Pavlova's broad experience, which varies from the design of master plans, urban design, interior design, design of schools, cultural centers, hotels, restaurants, housing, libraries, business centers, commercial centers, etc. The drawings cover several aspects of Pavlova's design activity in different periods. It starts with the project of Park Kenana dated 1964 and ends with the project of the Commercial center in Blagoevgrad designed in 1986 and completed in 1999.
The portfolio provides documentation about seven different projects via 87 photocopies of photographs, drawings, and newspaper clippings. The portfolio contains also photocopies of some of the Diploma that Pavlova received during her career.
The architectural drawings consist of 40 original drawings (ink on lucid paper and blueprints) documenting three projects from Bulgaria: the Hotel and restaurant "Nevrokop" in Gotse Delchev 1968-1976 (14 drawings), the Town hall in Gotse Delchev (reconstruction and addictions, not built, 1984 (11 drawings) and the Home of Books (Library, Bookstore, Exhibits) in Gotse Delchev, drawn in 1986, but not built (15 drawings). These projects are well documented by master plans, floor planes, sections and elevations (scale 1:200, 1:500).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
IAWA Small Collections, Ms2009-054. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Contents List
- Curriculum vitae. (Folder 1)
- Portfolio (89 pages), 1968-1999. (Folder 2)
  - Pg. 1-14 Hotel with Restaurant "Nevrokop" in Gotse Delchev designed in 1968 and completed in 1976.
    - 6 photographs (5 photocopies and one original).
    - Photocopies of newspaper clippings.
    - Photocopies of drawings:
      - Site plan.
      - Elevation of the building (scale 1:200).
      - Transversal section of the building.
      - (3) Floor planes (scale 1:100).
      - (3) Floor planes (scale 1:200).
  - Pg. 15 Photocopy of the Diploma obtained by participating in the Architectura Biennale in 1985 with the reconstruction of the center of Gotse Delchev.
  - Pg. 16 Photocopy of the Diploma and second prize in the national review "Historical themes in Art", held in Turnovo in 1985 for the Center of Gotse Delchev.
  - Pg. 17 Photocopies of material documenting that:
    - In 1971 Radka Pavlova was sent to Moscow (May 9-24) for "creative discussions" with soviet colleagues.
    - In 1993 she received the gold insignia of the Union of Architects in Bulgaria in conjunction with her 60th birthday.
    - In 1983 she received the medal "Cyril and methodizing."
  - Pg. 18-21(4) pages documentation regarding the project for the renovation and additions in the Center of Gotse Delchev:
    - Original photo of the model.
    - Original photo of a drawing plan.
    - (2) photocopies of drawings: Elevations of projected buildings surrounding the central plaza.
  - Pg. 22-37(16) photocopies documenting the project for the proposed reconstruction and additions of the Town hall in Gotse Delchev (design not executed):
    - Picture documenting the Town hall before reconstruction.
    - Floor plan of Town hall (existing building).
    - General site plan (scale 1:500).
    - (3) prospect of the building (scale 1:200).
    - (2) transversal section of the building (scale 1:200).
    - (8) plans of the building (scale 1:200, 1:100).
  - Pg. 38-44(7) photocopies documenting the project of 1986 for the library with reading rooms, exhibition space and store called "House of Books" in Gotze Delchev (not executed):
    - Site plan (scale 1:500).
    - Elevations (scale 1:200).
    - (4) floor plans (scale 1:200).
    - Transversal section elevation (scale 1:200).
  - Pg. 45-54(10) photocopies documenting the project for the Communist Party headquarters in Gotse Delchev, designed in 1985 (not executed):
    - Site plan (scale 1:500).
    - Photographs of the model.
    - (3) transversal section and elevations (scale 1:200).
    - (3) floor plans (scale 1:200, 1:500).
  - Pg. 55-67(13) photocopies documenting the project for the Post office and library-reading rooms in Gotse Delchev, completed in 1987:
    - (3) black and white and color photographs of the site and building.
    - (2) site plan, floor plans and elevations.
    - (3) elevations of the building (scale 1:200, 1:100).
    - (2) floor plans (scale 1:100).
    - Details for the partition of the windows.
    - Transversal section (1:50).
  - Pg. 68-72(5) photocopies documenting the project for the Master plan for remodeling and unifying the main commercial street in Gotse Delchev, designed in 1986 (not executed):
    - Master plan (scale 1:500).
    - (2) elevations (scale 1:500).
    - Floor plans (scale 1:500).
  - Pg. 73-75(3) photocopies documenting the project for the School in Melnik (designed in 1965, construction completed in 1968). For this design she has been recognized by the architectural profession (photographs, elevation, floor planes).
  - Pg. 76-78(3) photocopiesof newspaper clippings documenting the positive comment about the project for the Planning and Urban design for the ancient Bulgaria capital Preslav and the nearby historic remains in Patleina of 1965.
  - Pg. 79-81(3) photocopies documenting the project for the Restaurant and wine cellar Patleina, near Preslav, completed in 1971:
    - Photographs of the site before construction.
    - Photograph of the building.
    - Elevation of the building in color (scale 1:100).
  - Pg. 82-83(2) photocopies documenting the project for the Entrance gateway to the park "Kenana" in Khaskovo (design 1968, completion 1970):
    - Photographs of the building.
    - Details of the rest area.
  - Pg. 84 Photocopy of the Diploma received from the city of Grenoble, France in the 1991 for the Commercial Center, Blagoevgrad designed in 1986-93with architect Iskra Shtetinska).
  - Pg. 85-89(5) photocopies documenting the project of the Commercial Center in Blagoevgrad, designed in 1986 and completed in two stages (1987-1999):
    - (2) photographs of the presentation drawings.
    - Photograph of the model.
    - (2) photograph of the building, interiors and exteriors.
- Brochure regarding the project of the Commercial Center in Blagoevgrad designed in 1986 and completed in two stages, 1987-1999. (Folder 3)
- Magazine reporting an article about the Youth Center in Teven designed in 1968-69 by Radka Pavlova. (Folder 4)
- Hotel and Restaurant "Nevrokop" in Gotse Delchev, 1968-1976. (Folder 5)
  - Article published after construction documenting the project (Review title: Apxumekmypa n. 3-1981 pg. 16-20).
  - (14) Original drawings (ink on lucid paper):
    - 1-Site plan (scale 1:500) Legend: A-Hotel and restaurant; B-Coffee Shop; C-Art gallery; D-Existing church; E-Parking; F-Post office.
    - 2-Basement floor plan (scale 1:200).
    - 3-Ground floor plan with bar (scale 1:200).
    - 4-Plan of the 1st floor (scale 1:200).
    - 5-Plan of the 2nd floor (scale 1:200).
    - 6-Plan of the 3rd floor (scale 1:200).
    - 7-Plan of the 4th floor (scale 1:200).
    - 8-5th, 6th, 7th floor plan (scale 1:200).
    - 9-South east elevation facing the town's square (scale 1:200).
    - 10-North east elevation (scale 1:200).
    - 11-South west elevation (scale 1:200).
    - 12-Elevation facing the Pirin mountain (i.e. street elevation) (scale 1:200).
    - 13-Section (scale 1:200).
    - 14-Site plan, A-Ground floor plan, B-First floor plan, C-Upper floor plan, Section (scale 1:200, 1:500). Drawing prepared for an exhibition in France with titles in French.
- Town hall in Gotse Delchev (reconstruction and additions, not built), 1984. (Folder 6)
  - (11) Original drawings (ink on lucid paper). Master plan of town's center (scale 1:500):
    - 1-Town Hall.
    - 2-Communist Party head quarters.
    - 3-Youth center (existing).
    - 4-Library.
    - 5-Post office.
    - 6-Hotel.
    - 7-Museum.
    - 8-Monument to Gotse Delchev.
    - 9- Churches.
    - 10-Town's museum.
    - 11-Agricultural Industries plant.
  - Plan of the existing Town Hall.
  - Plan of the sub-basement (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of basement (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the 1st floor (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the 2nd floor (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the 3rd floor (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the attic floor (scale 1:200).
  - Roof plan (scale 1:200).
  - Sections (scale 1:200).
  - Elevations (scale 1:200).
  - Elevations and sections (scale 1:200).
- Home of Books (Library, bookstore, exhibits) in Gotse Delchev (design not built), 1968. (Folder 7)
  - (2) Master plan of town's center (scale 1:500).
  - (15) Original drawings (7 ink on lucid paper 1 blue print):
    - 1-Main town square.
    - 2-Party head quarters.
    - 3-Youth center.
    - 4-Town Hall.
    - 5-Professional union Headquarters.
    - 6-Post office.
    - 7-Monument.
    - 8-Library (Home of Books).
    - 9-Church.
    - 10-Existing building.
    - 11-Church.
    - 12-14-Existing houses.
    - 15-Hotel "Nevrokop."
  - Ground floor plan (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the 1st floor (scale 1:200).
  - Plan of the 2nd floor (scale 1:200).
  - Basement floor plan (scale 1:200).
  - Sections (scale 1:200).
  - East and north elevations (scale 1:200).
  - East (main) and north elevations (scale 1:200).
  - Communist party headquarters: elevation facing the town's square -- second option with three floors (scale 1:200).
  - Communist party headquarters: ground floor plans and section (scale 1:200, 1:500).
  - Communist party headquarters: 3 floor plans (scale 1:500).
  - Communist party headquarters: main elevation facing the town's square (scale 1:200).
  - Communist party headquarters: detail of the sequencing of the windows in the elevation (scale 1:50) -- pencil drawing.
  - Communist party headquarters: elevations (scale 1:200).